oh don't record I thought we could just
be silent today is that it is that good
is that okay let's just do that okay
then I can meditate instead of counting
breath trying to sound intelligent good
any questions no meditation questions
well okay
any question
[Applause]
thank you guys I love for teaching and
thank you for this wonderful Stylinson
pract the ability to do the meditation
on our own without guidance my question
comes roundabout again with what Arianna
Guardian is teaching of seeds and no
causes and no results basically or there
and the yelling husband as you know
recently I started working in a safe
house for people who are experiencing
domestic violence and you also teach the
four steps and so I'm trying to work
with this with people who are in that
situation because it can be a revolving
door situation and it's easy to teach
them about seeds but what about that
revolving door or them the fact that
whether they're men or women they keep
getting into that same situation or
going back into it and it's like how to
break that's that cycle at that moment
so that you can then plant seeds for the
future and so this is something I'm
working with with these people and I
would love some wisdom of how to work
with it thank you
yeah so first of all I think dissing
well there there is a gap between not
yelling back and the husband changing so
during that time if there's abuse right
physical verbal abuse emotional abuse
then then I think it's important for us
to tell people for Buddhists to tell
people you don't have to sit there
you're not supposed to sit there and do
nothing and wait for your seats to
change okay so I think it's important to
encourage people to get a break or take
care of themselves and go to a safe
house or you know so we're not saying
that you should understand the husband's
coming from you and stop yelling at
other people and then you know just go
through the abuse we're not saying that
so you should attempt to remove yourself
from the abuse and then people like you
to try to help people remove themselves
from the abuse but it may not work you
know because they haven't changed the
seats so I think but you still have to
try you still have to say you have to
you should leave here's the safe house
but things may get worse when they come
to the same same house you know so I
think that's important to tell people
question yeah so then also there's two
at least two people involved in this
there's the abuser and the abused and
they both we need to protect both of
them and help both of them not to
continue to produce those seeds it's
like I don't quite know how to do that
yeah I think there's also a thing of
capacity and opportunity it's I think
you have to have capacity and
opportunity so do you have the capacity
how many people can you teach at once am
i Lama thought he really changed to
people I knew him for thirty years he
changed to people during that time so
it's it's hard to change a person you
know I think so you have to be because
realistic about how much you can do
right now before you get a thousand arms
so I think you may not be able to help
the abuser and the abuse at the same
time you can try but I think also if you
overestimate your capacity you might not
be able to help either one sorry that I
think you have to in a practical way you
have to see how much you can do without
getting exhausted you know and there's a
big debate about you know the debate but
has the buddha perfected the two goals
you know is the buddha perfect and has
the buddha perfected the service of what
others need has the beautiful filled
with others need and they say yes this
is a debate at the beginning of the from
Antarctica
and they say yeah he has fulfilled
because he he has the best method but
that doesn't mean there's no more poor
people you see he he knows how to stop
poverty but then there's opportunity you
know will they listen to you
so there's capacity and there's an
opportunity will they take your advice
you know so I
they say the buddha has perfected what
others need just by being able to help
them if they choose to listen yeah so
that's the second thing I can think of
the third thing is what is it thinking
yeah
in this DCI we have a nice teaching
called the four flowers and the third
one is what you know that your
environment is coming from you also so
in a way it's helpful to everyone
involved should understand that the
person being abused and the person
abusing them are both coming from us you
see like you wouldn't see that's the
thing about the definition of the sample
the kind that you can only see 10th
level buddy stop us around you but they
may be seeing violence to each other
every day you see so really in the end
that's the emptiness of things right the
the things around you even the people
that you see are coming from you so one
way to help stop violence would be to
the abuser and the abuse is to see where
where are we abusing people in a small
way other question it's pretty long
yeah let's add other people
it's up to jaw and it's not my decision
it seems like at the beginning of the
meditation when we are perceiving the
noise of the fan we're perceiving things
incorrectly but then by the end of the
meditation when we are bringing the guru
down into our heart we're perceiving
things correctly so at what point in
between do we actually start perceiving
things correctly yeah good
and by the way wait wait right he's a
new staff member here and apparently
he's a maintenance master and he's been
fixing many many of your houses he has
this skill and I'd like to thank him
yeah there's the official start time and
there's the unofficial start time so you
know you're supposed to start seeing
things right as you as you go to your
past life so in theory as you observe
your past life you are still seeing
things that's coming from their own Sun
you see
otherwise we would have a fake past life
and a real person life you see it I mean
we would be saying like I was
interesting I I spent the day yesterday
with Michael and Melissa so in my past
life today I was pregnant which I never
thought of doing
[Laughter]
but while I'm looking at the pregnant
lady who's me if I don't
yeah we're not even supposed to be
thinking that she's she's coming from my
seats the imagination of it it's also
coming from my seats probably they're
the same seat that why I see Melissa
pregnant or or Katie yeah like I I agree
with I think you could kick it in any
time yeah officially you're supposed to
think that things are fake second
husband officially you're supposed to do
after the past life thing so after you
finished that the gardener would say
where's the line when you stop thinking
about your past my what today I guess
but I think you're right I think it
might be really useful to start thinking
about the fake pregnant lady okay good
it's up to Joe Ciera ray Hodges Tosha
the one case mentioned Ont
tion-tion-tion so she attends er E so
Tommy giana's Oh nan foe Sequoia Frank
Allen Poe finito Mata soy un sitio fan
oh ha ha kodesh really Oz she turns over
engine turns over the East region
so she ham ham people at a cancer know
where Sun Sutra we are welcome
Oh Castle Oh cousin some users over okay
hon hon John Stanton tahun pp - she she
she I prefer the Oppo phone oh a
Chilean Thai English the whole our
[Laughter]
[Music]
vacation sister CSP she's the first CSP
oh yeah
yeah so the question is when I do lion
stands at my house I spent like 40 to 50
minutes on the first part then I learned
part one to five but when I reach
usually when the TV fine now I learn all
five cards and then usually when I have
done 40 minutes I feel very tired and I
want to go to PP so do I have to finish
all five parts at one section or can I
separate and in my daily practice for
sure you can take a break and you can
you know I think it's impossible I'm not
I mean the goal is to do all five parts
but it may take you a year or something
I you know during the she's from our
China South Power Program which is where
Chinese executives are learning ancient
culture to take on the one belt one road
to internationally and it's 40 select
business owners so she's the first one
to come to the moon so I'd like to thank
so yeah we had a interesting idea I just
occurred to me one day in the CSP
program was to tell these business
owners just add a minute every week add
one minute every week and that comes
from my three-year retreat when I was in
Tamara gene I had a book by a yoga
teacher David Swensen
it's an Ashtanga book and so I wrote him
you know during my break I said I wrote
Jigme I think I said can you invite
David Swensen he's like one of the most
famous new yoga teachers you know I
think invite him to come out we were in
the desert near here that's about it's
about an hour from here we were in a
very empty place and in 5000 acres and
which we borrowed and then he did come
he agreed to comment it's like a miracle
and we didn't pay anything you know and
he just thought it was cool and weird so
he came I remember he came in the winter
and it was very cold and he said touch
your touch your toes and I'm like I
can't and then he came back with a
telephone book and he said touch the
telephone book and I like this is in the
days of telephone books and I had
touched the telephone book and then he
said tear out one page each day and I'm
like like like a thousand pages there he
says you're in three-year between
so I did I turn out a face each day and
then I can touch my daughter and so I
think same with this yeah so if you have
to break and that's fine that's
wonderful
don't don't worry about it yeah you
might have to break a few times and I
think for you guys CSP people you're
busy so maybe only on the weekend you
can you can do a fire
in China we can start Saturday afternoon
right some countries like that yeah
Saturday Sunday second seal our Chilean
side high English how can you come since
April fun so she she she allows NATO
from Yoda also touted she shall ano see
you kappa :
China comes in or - she outsider cocoons
en chicken show to the kanji that she
says she's a also handsome George she
she Allah - I prefer Russia when the one
t-shirt a porphyrin yeah we are chatting
she she she second part is last time
when you taught in Thailand for the lion
stance
you taught us to fake teacher and you
taught us to cancel the teacher and
enter into the space where the
impassible teacher where there's an
impassable space that's what she said
but this time you didn't teach this part
so I wonder why and how can I practice
if I want to enter that space of
emptiness because you said entering that
space supposed to help us understand
yeah I did it better in Thailand
so follow Thailand and maybe tomorrow
I'll record the whole five parts and
I'll do it that way it's better yeah
you're right let's do it
we didn't do the formless realms
yesterday and let's finish those and
then we'll take a pee-pee break okay so
I won't I'll try to go fast through the
formulas room because we still have form
if I can find it
somebody asked me for my notes and
you're always welcome to have my notes
but I translate things unofficially for
myself so then somebody told me they
showed it to some professor and I'm like
that's not a good idea because it's not
finished
it's just my notes to myself and in many
cases it's not it's not correct yet so
okay but you're welcome to have no it's
and like commonly Sheila a lot of it's
in English and but it's all unofficial
okay it's messy not it's not perfect I
don't like to give out things that
aren't perfect
Nikki knows so okay Carol from Taiwan
it's gonna I do want to just say Sachi
and then go wah wah wah then after that
go
[Music]
and
and make
[Music]
to
turn to
me
[Music]
absolutely
all right then ready for four formulas
rooms and the fifth one is called pipi
place and again I'm in some Karpis now
now we're switching from so Kappa
yesterday was from so now and some copy
is about 200 years after so Noah and
this is from this explanation of the
jewel of realizations by a Samba it's an
interesting text cuz he wrote it very
young I think he was under 30 or
something and it's huge
and it's interesting to see his
development over time sorry Sigma Xi
Lanham katha okay Jamie when we talk
about the four formless realms the first
one is called infinite space okay so
don't get confused the ocean is space
okay it's supposed to be it's called
infinite space so as I said yesterday
that for formula realm levels get boring
names number one number two number three
number four but the four formless realm
meditations have sexy names and the
first one's called infinite space again
it's not that your body at least is in
the formless realm it's that if you do
this meditation a lot then you'll be
reborn into the and if I died right here
I would enter the formless realm right
here and
there's not much need for Bardo so Bardo
purpose is to get to your next planet or
your next country and if you enter the
formulas realm you kind of don't go
anywhere so there's been debate about
the Bardo for formulas so I would just
enter then there's a debate about well
how about lung some Juke but cheaper
ones than me
take it yeah prana in the mind right
together like a horse and a horse rider
so how can you have thought without
prana if you're in a formless realm and
then the conclusion of the Scriptures is
that you still have some form you still
have some subtle prana and your mind is
riding on a very subtle prana
but here you can't you have no visible
body okay all right so here's the first
one if you keep doing this many hours a
day for many years you will be born into
this formulas round okay and Buddhists
consider it sort of waste of time okay
it's like doing Netflix from morning
tonight I mean there are times when you
should do that like after a long tiring
retreat
but generally you don't want to do it
all the time
okay if you do it all the time you'll be
born into the forum okay
so we can see it as kind of just a delay
you're just wasting time you know
there's a depressing point of view
expressed by Master Saturday more than
if you waste a day on Netflix that you
don't need okay there's days when you
need to do Netflix all day like you're
exhausted like Michael and Melissa
should do it for one day before your
next guests show up and then your next
guests show up
so that's okay
but Judy EMA says okay if if you'd like
to be responsible for the suffering of
seven billion people for another day
yeah that's okay you need to bring you
know you know just delay your Buddhahood
one more day you know then you feel
guilty super guilty you have to balance
these two things there is a time when
you should watch Netflix something okay
if you can find anything interesting
okay super on topic douchey rock part on
me so there's always this process in
moving between the eight levels of a
gotcha I'm not gonna offer any money cuz
Nick looks like he remembers what's it
mean
[Music]
yeah what you deny so there's two kinds
of gotcha
one is the absence of an impossible
thing like the second husband
that's called the gotcha and then
there's Lanka gotcha which is something
that really does exist like the
Christmas tree okay
and that's means the fourth form room
level the crystal the sugar crystal you
get bored and you say I want quieter
it's not quite enough for me or I want
to exercise my mind you know this is
still form okay I want to go to no form
okay form looks too physical to me and I
would like to go to a place where
there's no physical okay so you're
supposed to have this kind of motivation
when you move from the sugar crystal to
the ocean you know I want to drop all
limitations physical limitations I want
to open up it's similar to the darker
and the jailer what's that
yeah and that that's what gets you out
of the desire realm when you move from
desire realm which is the air
conditioner to the first form realm
which is your heart beating you are
rejecting something
okay that's gotcha you'd like all the
desire realms to it's too gross for me I
want something more subtle like my
heartbeat you're doing the same thing
when you move from the form round to the
formless room you see you're like I want
a new kind of challenge I I'm tired of
being in this little sugar crystal yeah
let's open things up let's not limit
ourselves physically okay sit down
douche a rock but Tommy soup soup tongue
top a douche a it says physicality and
concreteness something hard I want to
drop this idea of something hard okay -
she means Concepcion do Jeon tae yong
doing number Sheikh Jing nan khatai asan
younger - Shay
so you keep physical things keep coming
up in your mind and you you block them
and you start to expand like the ocean
so you drop physic physical perception
and you go to more mental okay and then
you you get this feeling like oh this
feels like endless this ocean feels like
the sky it feels like endless okay like
that tie a combo chip a this is the comb
it's not gone and now that we've been in
translation class for two years ya know
that's common core means get used to it
okay you get you start to get used to
the company Moshi do sir Taemin the
cupid say it's MJ g % untouchable then
after this kind of preliminary period
where you're moving from the formula to
the for
which is called neon dog that's called
the neon that means like the opening act
the small band that plays for the big
band okay neo means that so that's why
you're deciding to get out of the sugar
crystal you're not really into the
formless realm yet you're just the
opening band
this is opening bands time and then you
get used to being in the formulas room
and we call that mushy mushy means the
then you reach the middle of that level
okay while you're transitioning while
you're moving from form to formless your
mind is still not formless so we don't
count it as formless realm the real
thing it's not the main band yet the
main band that's playing it's just a
warm-up
there's a small band placed before the
big pin and when you reach the big band
that single pointed focus on infinite
infinity is the first formal formulas
room okay cool
single point in this one infinity has
then the real one not the warm-up not
the transition right okay and you'll get
used to it you'll say oh I must be in
the first part and now I'm in the main
part and now I'm getting ready to move
to the second formulas ma'am okay so if
you have lots of time if you have like
three hours free
you know drink a coffee between every
level I'm kidding okay all right
second level for most is called infinite
consciousness and here's how some copper
describes it namja tak Cheney by the way
those of you who are learning to then
this is also called a kitchen which here
it doesn't mean a sense door it just
means a stage or something okay what is
this sounds great I had done yeah okay
I'm sure tying a kitchen in naan khatai
so number you cheating so each a means
to think about the place where you're at
and think oh spaces I'm sorry I'm sorry
that's the gotcha here the gotcha good
the gotcha is the feeling that things
are infinite got it okay the old first
level feeling that things are infinite
becomes an obstacle okay to go in deeper
so at the first formless realm you have
feelings of infinity and then those
feelings become an obstacle okay and you
want to move to the second god chart
painting got chart any means tweet those
feelings of infinity as a gotcha okay
see them take department our see them as
a as a now they're holding you back
they're limiting u infinity is limiting
you okay that make a nice first line of
a song okay
Dini Egypt any ties or young to you you
know JP so you ready
you gotta put on your seat belt
I'm sorry in the first formulas round
you're focusing on infinity the ocean
and then you say oh that's infinite you
know that's cool
but then after a while you're like is
there any place deeper to go and then
you realize that the state of mind which
is focusing on infinity is more deep
than the infinity okay got it
so there's a connection between the
first one and the second one in the
first formulas realm you are focusing on
infinity okay and you watch the Infinity
for a while I follow the ocean I check
out surf spots in Bali and Mexico K 49
in Baja and I go around different places
and then I come back and then you're
like well there's nothing else to do and
then you say oh I could explore the
infinity of the state of mind which is
watching infinity got it
so the second is called num Cheeta
infinite awareness okay so you're
blocking the Infinity because it's too
gross it's not subtle enough and then
you say well what's more subtle than
none huh my mind is more subtle than
then you know my mind is stretching
infinitely so you come into the infinity
of your mind which is the subject during
the first four most relevant level got
it okay so during the first formless
realm lhamo you're watching the object
of infinity during the second formless
realm level which is called infinite
awareness you are watching your
awareness of infinity okay and that's
more infinite and that's where we've
been going to outer space since to think
that okay all right
and then the Gipper them then third
level is called Jian man say to young
man it's a very famous name because it's
very sexy and very wrong okay and there
were famous monks who made the mistake
of saying this was emptiness this is the
perception of emptiness and then there
were famous debates in like the eighth
century ninth century and people people
prove them wrong okay so this is it
feels cool but it's not emptiness okay
so that's a when you explain the third
formless realm level to somebody you're
always supposed to say don't stay there
and this is not emptiness okay so here's
the description by Tom kappa chiyo maybe
catch any day of the song j'tia madonna
of the yellow changing moon decrepit on
oh but when I'm focusing on my mind as
it focuses on infinity with on the
second level second formless level it
would be cooler if I just dropped all
focus all objects so not even my mind so
in the first level you drop the object
of infinity in the second level you're
watching your mind the subject becomes
the object in the second number then
when you get to the third level you're
like you know it'd be more cool to just
drop everything
no infinity no mind watching infinity
okay just drop it off and that's called
Qi young me young man means nothing at
all there was a famous serial
advertisement okay the last time I
watched TV was with my llama
1998 and I think you know mostly and
then there was a commercial for cereal
called nuts and honey and the wife comes
in and says what are you eating and he
says nothing honey not nothing honey
nothing but sounds like nuts and honey
anyway BuChE BuChE should wait but
should the methyl methyl mei-fun push it
- okay no honey made for me
push it upon me yeah nothing honey and
anyway this name of this level is
nothing nothing nothing at all it means
nothing to me that was pretty bad okay
I'll stop trying - sure do shi Mei Ming
he catch any I'm in a good mood some
people know why Shan Mei make Kate a
knee okay the next level has a weird
name the fourtner yeah - shaimaa do
shame amen
say do shame me to shame amen
neither neither no thoughts nor not no
thoughts okay neither no thoughts nor
not nor thoughts neither thinking or not
thinking
neither thinking not thinking and also
not not thinking it's the name of the
llama okay I didn't write it the Buddha
did okay but I think it'd be a good name
for a band
okay we keep looking for names it's the
hardest thing in the world to think of a
name for your band okay dear shame a
minke kitchen addition in dead and dead
I'm some solution map and a good the
mobile
then they think about a quotation by
Lord Buddha who said the act of thinking
is a sickness and it's pain it's painful
to think that they think about Buddha
said you know when you think it's like a
sickness and it's painful
okay then Buddha said but not thinking
is to is to stay in the darkness not
thinking is to stay in the darkness to
think it's painful to not think is is to
be in the darkness
do you mean me me me Shiva then the
Buddha said if you could stay between
those two it would be peace Xuan
candomblé nick for $20 caliber yeah I
forget that okay beautiful it would be
lovely
let's go mmm hang on and Guapo it means
go up on exactly cutie cutie pie okay
channel button say khandoba
so if you want a compliment tibetan lady
you can see a number but the word is
2,000 years old so surprising huh
[Laughter]
new unit a patina new japa new pair
sensitive parts and eligible so it's a
staying in that trying to stay between
thinking and not thinking try to stay
between thinking and not thinking and
this is where you do not try to block
the thoughts but you don't engage with
them okay then is a symptom than some
dent on Chapa okay in each you wanna
take a shot at that neck something
something it's something not
five ways that the main mind is linked
to the mental function there's five ways
that the main mind is linked to mental
functions so he says don't forget that
although we're talking about a mental
function
what's the mental function that we're
talking about which mental function is
always there during meditation
well that's general that's main mind
yeah focus Sam teaching in Kagura okay
single point in mind he says don't
forget with all of these descriptions
we're not talking about focus alone
we're talking about focus attached
connected with your whole mind with
awareness okay sorry it's not only focus
it's the whole mind okay we're gonna do
three things we're gonna read one more
sentence which is his criticism of the
eight levels his warning package when he
called on the cigarette package warning
luck label could cause cancer use wisely
okay yeah so we're gonna do that then
I'm gonna do the opening ceremony so you
can talk when you go peepee alright and
that's just a five minute thing I
promise
and then can we do you when we get back
Melissa and then we're gonna take a
break and then Melissa is gonna come
back and empty your pockets but for
diamond mom okay here's some coppers
Rico warning labor after he teaches the
these levels he says no more change is
something I'm not the devil erroneous
episode shared among the total loss of
autonomy ketchup and power she chewed on
some tanki SEM King Bangladeshi children
drank etomidate Alamein anjum said some
you know there's four problems he
says four warnings for warnings okay
number one don't get attached to the
taste of these meditations especially
the last two you know don't stop there
and say oh this is feel so nice
okay because while you're thinking that
your body is collapsing okay
your body's getting older if you stay in
the last two levels for an hour
you're an hour closer to your death your
body is not in the meditation your
body's getting older okay two more
harris got green during that hour
okay got it so don't don't think this is
the gone this is not the gone okay he
says number one number two non guitar
Ta'ala sapa town yom kippur chiba he
says these meditations can lead to the
mistake of believing there was a
beginning to samsara there was a
beginning to your mind these meditations
can lead you into the mistake of
believing there's a beginning say geez
trying to figure out why and tell us
later cuz I also don't know okay we have
to think about it it's that we have to
think about it okay I I also haven't
thought about it and so I'm not going to
give you an answer my llama say the you
cooking
okay third one something kissed em
camping Nadia if you get good at sitting
for two hours without moving because you
can put your mind in these infinity
places you will develop Prime you know
I'm a real practitioner I can sit for
two hours without moving you know you
never know what's going on inside of a
person's mind when they're sitting for
two hours meditating okay but the Sakya
say 12 minutes it's it's about the
amendment of a normal person okay 12
minutes of true focus it's about the
limit of a normal person so I I'm I
would say you know and I've done three
retreats I've done about 20 with two
month retreats and yeah I think that's
about right real focus you know if you
sit for three hours you you probably
will not benefit okay and probably
you're just trying to show off okay all
right okay fourth one so so many short
meditations it's better for all of us
doesn't matter how long you've been
meditating okay
Rangi tapa de Ptolemy nom nom in satsang
Shh our you will start to believe you
will start to suspect that especially
the seventh and eighth ones are nirvana
okay you will make that mistake you will
think these two levels are nirvana so
that's some coppers warning about this
eh okay I like to warn people then
there's also listed that
you will become forgetful okay you would
like leave your phone somewhere and all
your friends are always irritated and
she's the girl who always leaves her
phone somewhere did you remember to turn
on location services that you spaced out
about everything okay so that's a danger
of this meditation all right I promised
you a break right
okay break